What therapies outside of oral
medications do you see helpful to men
with sexual function concerns?
>> So, a pretty much everyone if you don't
live under a rock has heard of Viagra,
Seialis, and Levitra. And I know a lot
of guys um on this forum have heard a
lot about daily lowd dose sealis or
tadalapil which has a lot of great
benefits to it. Um, so I won't go in too
much on that because that's already been
discussed thoroughly. Um, those are
great uh kind of spot check treatment
options I think. Um, but not looking at
the underlying cause of vascular
dysfunction.
I think in my mind about four main
causes of sexual performance issues. um
hormonal
uh side effects of other medications
um vascular and then psychossematic and
depending on who you ask uh you will get
different answers on which one of those
is most common uh you know for everybody
um I see that it's usually a combination
of a few of those things. So most guys
want to know why you know if your
testosterone is optimized why are you
still having erectile dysfunction
issues? Um, if you look at what other
medications they're on, their history,
their age, um, ask them about things
like morning erections, um, are they
able to get as good of erections by
themselves as they are with a partner.
That can help you rule out if there's a
psychosmatic reason, performance
anxiety, or um, if you don't like your
partner, something like that. Um, so
when you think about if it's more likely
a vascular issue, that sometimes does
improve over time when you have the
hormones optimized and you're dieting
and exercising right for a consistent
period of time. Um, but that can take a
while. Um, and that's why a lot of guys
will use the daily seialis, but
sometimes that's not enough either. Um
so the other therapies that I really
like um kind of starting with the most
non-invasive I guess there is um vacuum
pump devices. These you can think about
as uh penile rehabilitation. I know
everyone has Austin powers come to mind
when they initially hear vacuum pump
device. Um but you got to kind of get
over that um mental hurdle and think of
it as going to the gym. So, if you
previously had really good morning
erections and you don't anymore, um
morning erections is like your penis
going to the gym every day. Um it's
preparing for the real thing. And if
you're not getting those anymore, then
you're having that loss of uh exercise,
loss of blood flow, which is an
important function. So, the vacuum pump
device helps to mimic that activity. It
helps get blood flow into the tissue,
which is going to improve um um the
quality of erections when you're
actually attempting to get an erection.
Doing that two or three times a week um
using a device that ideally has a gauge
on it so that you don't overdo it um I
think can be a really good at home tool
for people. Um outside of that, the next
thing that I would mention is wave
therapy. Wave therapy is using acoustic
sound waves to break up plaque inside
the vessels and it actually causes a
little bit of micro trauma. So it
stimulates the body to bring in growth
factors and healing factors so that you
can repair and heal those um blood
vessels that may have had damage with
age as well. Um the complimentary
treatment to that is PRP. You can think
about these both as by themsel or in
conjunction. I really like using them
both together, doing six to 12 sessions
of wave therapy and then one or two um
procedures of PRP because if you think
about the wave therapy as like getting
all the weeds out of your garden and
then the PRP like planting the new seeds
for new growth, that's how it's working
in your body. the PRP um is triggering
your body to have that better growth,
healing, and repair to happen. Um where
guys are really noticing a lot of
improvement from wave therapy in
sensation, firmness, blood flow, and
then the PRP builds on that and you can
potentially see some improvement in size
like girth as well.
>> You do present them to men in the order
that you just uh presented it. you start
with the the least invasive?
>> Not necessarily. I guess it depends on
the situation. Um the vacuum pump device
always goes alongside PRP. So if they're
doing PRP, they're going to do a vacuum
pump um twice a day for six weeks
following their PRP injections. Um this
is going to help tremendously with the
benefits. with both wave therapy and PRP
the results are not immediate. So they
do take some time for you to see those
uh results but you know looking at our
patient outcomes we've done a lot of
internal review of those things we use
the shim score which is looking at the
degree of sexual dysfunction. um the
patient is grading that on uh a
questionnaire and prior to wave therapy
if they were at moderate for erectile
dysfunction we're getting a whole
category of improvement meaning they're
going to mild erectile dysfunction. Um
so then you know they could just add on
doing more wave therapy to try to get
further improvement. Sometimes they're
happy with where they're at. Um, but um,
you know, you don't have to go forward
everybody. That scares a lot of guys
away thinking about injecting some
penis, but there are a lot of benefits
to PRP.
>> Sure. Um, and do you do this uh next to
the oral medication? Uh, I guess
>> Seialis is great to use alongside the uh
PRP, the wave therapy, and vacuum pump
because it it's going to help with that
penile rehab. it's going to keep
improving that the blood flow and um
oftentimes they can get off of it if
they want to. Many guys like it so they
stay on it. Um but you definitely can
use any of the oral medications, even
the higher dose as needed alongside of
these. Um most guys doing these
regenerative therapies have the goal of
eventually using less medication or
they're doing it because they're seeing
that they're not getting as good of
results as what they used to to their
oral medication. So, at some point
they're going to max out on the dose of
Viagra and they're like afraid that it's
just not gonna work. Um, a big
misconception I see though is that guys
are coming in once they're at that point
and they think, "Okay, now I have to do
something that's like more extreme and
do this wave therapy." Um, I see that
wave therapy works best if you have mild
issues or if you're doing it
preventatively. I think that's great too
because you know you're getting in
before it becomes a major problem versus
if somebody already has very severe ED
and you can't really get an erection at
all. It's going to take a lot more time,
effort, and more p
uh more procedures or sessions of wave
therapy for you to actually get better
results. Mhm. Are all men that come to
you with sexual dysfunction, are they
all low testosterone or not necessarily?
>> Um, well, if you're using the standard
guideline definition of low
testosterone, then no, they're not all
low testosterone. But, um, there are
some people I I think what you're
getting at is is everyone on
testosterone treatment or pursuing
testosterone treatment if they're doing
these sexual treatments? Um, and usually
we we almost always have somebody do a
full lab panel with us and do a full
consultation with hormones as the first
step. There are some guys who refuse it
and they've had their testosterone
checked with their primary and they have
no interest in exploring hormone
treatments um and can't be convinced
otherwise. And so they they certainly
can just pursue sexual health
treatments. um as as we all know that
there are a lot of people with normal
ranges of testosterone that um when we
give them a little bit more they don't
they don't have any sexual dysfunction.
So that's always the first thing that we
check off the box is making sure their
hormones are optimized and their
lifestyle habits are um ideally at least
being worked on. um you know the people
who are smokers and you know on five
different medications that might be
impacting their results to this you know
it it's tough because you know you you
want them to see benefits to everything
that they're doing. So um in many cases
I don't even recommend these treatments
to someone who's in that situation. um
if if they're not in a a generally good
healthy place, they might not see a
whole lot of results. A good example of
what I mean by this is um I had a guy
that came in to do PRP for the first
time and he swore up and down that he
was following a really good healthy diet
and exercise and he had no idea why he
has erectile dysfunction and you know
he's just so stressed out about it. Um
and we drew his blood and I came in to
do it and I said I'm I'm really unsure
if we should do this. your PRP. Um um
you know, it looks like milk. It it
looks really bad. Um like what did you
eat before you came in here? He's like,
"Oh, I eat really healthy." And uh
eventually he told me he ate a sleeve of
chocolate chip cookies because he was
stressed out before coming in. And then
it made him even more stressed that I
told him his his blood looked terrible.
Um but you're you know, you're not
possibly going to get great results from
doing PRP when you have a really bad
sample. It's your own blood uh product
that's going back in. So, it should be
this like golden yellow color, almost
looks a little bit like urine. Um,
shouldn't be super cloudy. Um, and if
you're injecting a bad product, you're
not going to get good results.